Guide to the David Shub Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Shub papers
1912-1963
MS 607
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
Letters received by David Shub, author and friend of the Russian revolution. The letters are nearly all in Russian and are from various friends and associates of his in Europe and America.
Shub, David, 1887-1973
Biographical / Historical
DAVID SHUB 1887-1973
David Shub was born in Russia in 1887 and educated there. Over a period of more than fifty years he has had intimate contact with the leaders of every faction in the Russian revolutionary movement, both as a revolutionary and as a close student of Russian affairs.
Mr. Shub became a member of the Russian Social Democratic Party in 1903, at a time when Lenin was one of its leaders. From 1904 to 1905 he lived in the western European centres of Russian revolutionary activity (London, Paris, Geneva), where he often met Lenin and the other leaders of the Social Democratic Party - Bolshevik and Menshevik.
In September 1905 Mr. Shub returned to Russia and participated in the Russian Revolution of 1905-1906. Late in 1906 he was arrested for revolutionary activity and sentenced to exile in Siberia, whence he escaped a year later.
He arrived in the United States in 1908. Since then he maintained close contact with the leading figures of the Russian revolutionary movement and has written extensively on Russian affairs. He was personally acquainted with many of the Bolshevik leaders, including Lenin, Trotsky, and Bukharin, as well as with the outstanding liberals and socialists.
For many years he edited and contributed to liberal, labour and socialist publications in several languages.
He died in 1973.
Taken from Pelican Book A809: Lenin: A Biography by David Shub
Scope and Contents
Letters received by David Shub, author and friend of the Russian revolution. The letters are nearly all in Russian and are from various friends and associates of his in Europe and America.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Radicalism; Revolutionaries -- Soviet Union; Europe; Russia -- History -- Revolution, 1905-1907; Abramovich, R.; Balabanoff, Angelica, 1878-1965; Berline, Pavel; Bourtzeff, Vera; Černov, Viktor; Dan, Lidii͡a; Deĭch, L. G. (Lev Grigorʹevich), 1855-1941; Figner, Vera, 1852-1942; Karpovich, Michael, 1888-1959; Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1886-1957; Nikolayewsky, B. I.; Kuskova, Ekaterina; Samoĭlovna, Maria; Shub, David, 1887-1973; Vol'skiĭ, Nikolaĭ Vladislavovich, 1879-1964
- To David Shub from R. Abramovich
  - 1925 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1925 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1925 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1926 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1937 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- To David Shub from M. A. Aldonov
  - 1941 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1941 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1941 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1946 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1946 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1946 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1947 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1947 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1947 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1948 February 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1949 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1950 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1950 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- To David Shub from Dr. Angelica Balabanoff
  - 1948 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1948 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1951 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1952 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Undated (2) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- To David Shub from Pavel Berline
  - 1945 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [1945 May 15] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1946 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1946 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1946 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 [Mar?] 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 [Apr?] 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 [Aug?] 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1948 [February 20?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1948 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1948 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1949 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 [Mar?] 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1949 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1950 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1950 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1950 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1951 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [195?] August [20?] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ? Sep23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ? November 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Undated (2) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- To David Shub from Vera Bourtzeff
  - 1934 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1938 [June 26?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- To David Shub from Viktor Cernov
  - 1935 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1937 January 19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Undated (4) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- To David Shub from Lydia Dan
  - 1946 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1948 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1950 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1950 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1953 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1953 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1954 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1957 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1959 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1959 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1961 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- To David Shub from Lev Deich
  - 1912 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1912 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1912 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1915 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1921 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1922 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1922 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1922 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1922 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1923 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1923 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1923 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1923 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1923 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [1923?] April 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1923 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1924 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ? August 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Undated (2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- To David Shub from Lev Deich
  General
  Carbon copies of some of the above letters.
  - 1922 August 30 (two copies) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1922 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1922 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1923 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1923 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1924 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ? April 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- To David Shub from Vera Figner
  - 1926 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1927 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1928 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1928 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Envelope - no letter (Box 1, Folder 11)
- To David Shub from M. Karpovich
  - 1947 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1947 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1947 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1947 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1947 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1948 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1948 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1949 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1953 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1958 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- To David Shub from B.I. Nikolayewsky
  - 1939 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1940 January 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- To David Shub from Mrs. Cat. Prokopovich
  - 1950 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1950 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1952 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1952 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- To David Shub from [Nikolai Vladislavovich?] Volskij
  - 1934 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1938 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1938 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1945 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1945 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1945 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1945 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1946 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1946 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1946 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1946 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1946 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1946 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1946 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1946 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1947 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 May [26?] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 August [16?] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1947 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1948 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1948 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1948 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1948 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1948 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1948 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1948 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1948 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1949 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1949 ? 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1950 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1950 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1951 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1951? [29?] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1952 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 March [10?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 September [2?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1952 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1953 January [29?] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1953 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1954 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1954 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1954 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1954 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1954 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1954 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1954 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1957 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 November 20 (Copy) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1957 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1963 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1963 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Undated (2) (Box 1, Folder 27)
- From Volskij to Maria Samoilovna
  - 1949 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- From Doubleday and Company to Unknown
  - 1948 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 29)